Based on a true story.
Monster is a crime, drama film directed by Patty Jenkins.
In 1989, prostitute Aileen Wuornos befriends and enters a
relationship with a young woman named Selby.
Determined to straighten out her life, Aileen's limited
education lands her back on the corner.
She's raped by a trick, who she kills.
A string of murder and robbery follows that ultimately leads Aileen
to becoming America's first female serial killer.
Aileen Wuornos, played by Charlize Theron.
Selby Wall, played by Christina Ricci.
Thomas, played by Bruce Dern.
Vincent Corey, played by Lee Tergesen.
Donna, played by Annie Corley.
Gene / Stuttering "John", played by Pruitt Taylor Vince.
Monster is a 2003 American biographical crime drama film written and
directed by Patty Jenkins in her feature directorial debut.
The film follows serial killer Aileen Wuornos, a street prostitute who murdered seven of
her male clients between 1989 and 1990 and was executed in Florida in 2002.
It stars Charlize Theron as Wuornos and Christina Ricci as her semi-fictionalized
lover, Selby Wall (based on Wuornos's real-life girlfriend, Tyria Moore).
Monster had its world premiere at the AFI Fest on November 16, 2003.
On February 8, 2004, it premiered at the 54th Berlin International Film Festival, where it
competed for the Golden Bear, while Theron won the Silver Bear for Best Actress.
The film was theatrically released in the United States
on December 24, 2003, by Newmarket Films.
Monster received positive reviews from critics and achieved box office
success, grossing $64.2 million on a $1.5 million budget.
The film received numerous awards and nominations, particularly for Theron's performance, including the Academy Award for Best Actress, the Golden Globe Award for Best Actress in a Drama, the SAG Award for
Outstanding Lead Actress, the Critics' Choice Movie Award for Best Actress, the Independent Spirit Award for Best Female Lead, and also the Independent Spirit Award for Best First Feature (Patty Jenkins).
Theron's acting has continued to receive critical acclaim; film critic Roger Ebert called
Theron's role "one of the greatest performances in the history of the cinema".
The film was chosen by the American Film Institute
as one of the top ten films of 2003.
The film explores themes of death penalty,
prostitute, rape, sexual abuse, motel.
The tone is emotional.